<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise co[n]cernynge diuers of the constitucyons prouynciall and legantines</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853720</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853720</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19114</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68826)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19114)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 8:9, 18:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise co[n]cernynge diuers of the constitucyons prouynciall and legantines</title>
                  <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Godfray. Cum priuilegio regali,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1535?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Christopher Saint German.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁶.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10084 on UMI microfilm reel 8.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Cambridge University Library and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 8 (Cambridge University Library copy) and at reel 18 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:1"/>
            <p>¶ A treatiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge diuers of the conſtituty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons prouynciall and legantines,</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Printed at London by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Godfray. Cum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilegio regali.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Introduction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this lytell treatyſe are contayned dyuers thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges concernyng the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytutions prouynciall &amp; the legantynes / of Othe and Octobone / ſomtyme legates in this realme. And the matters that in treateth of be ſhortely touched in .xxx chapiters / whiche be ſette in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ende of this preſent treatiſe / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appereth that diuers of the ſaid conſtytutyons and legantynes be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the kynges lawes &amp; his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatyue. And that ſome of them be alſo very troublous vnto the people / and nat ſo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable as they ought to haue ben.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:2"/>
            <head>The fyrſt chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the conſtytutions prouiciall in the firſt boke / and in the tytle of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions: there is a decre / whiche be gynneth. <hi>Quia inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentie uicium et infra.</hi> Wherby it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that the conſtitucyon of the late lorde Octobon / agaynſte concubinaryes be inuyolably obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / and that it be recyted openly in the foure princypall chapiters rurall of the yere / before all the chapiter ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cludynge thens / and ſeperatynge all lay perſons. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſtitucions be good and neceſſary. But why laye perſonnes ſhulde be ſeperate fro the ſeyde recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talle: I ſe no cauſe / for if laye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons might be there alſo to here it / it wolde bothe do them good / and alſo make the ſpirituall men the beter to take hede. And ſyth laye men here of the defaultes and abuſyons at home where they dwell. What hurte could
<pb facs="tcp:19114:3"/>it do / if they herde the lawes that the clergye hath made for a reformation of them: But it is verye lyke that / that excludynge of laye men fro the redynge of the ſayde conſtitucyon: proceded of a drede / that the prelates at the makynge of the ſeyd conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon had: leſt that laye men / if they herde it / ſhulde happely the rather diſdayn preſtes or diſpyſe them: but ſurely it is to feare that / that drede ꝓceded nat of charite / but of ſigula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte / for by reaſon therof / I ſuppoſe the mater is come to that effecte / that it is neither red to preeſtes / ne yet to laye men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The ſeconde chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in the conſtytution / whiche begynneth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quod in conſtitutione et infra,</hi> And it is in the fyrſt boke / in the tytle of the Iteracyon of the ſacramentes / 
<pb facs="tcp:19114:3"/>to be done / or nat done. After the vii. Sacramentes be there reſyted / it is ſayde thus. But the .vi. ſacrament that is to ſaye of holy orders / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to they in that be parfyte. And the ſeuynth ſacrament / that is to ſay of Matrymonye / in the tyme of the Newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t accordeth to imꝑfet. And though it be trewe / that ſome that be in holy orders be more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that be in matrimony / yet to make a recytall in the lawe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally that the one order / that is to ſay preſtehode accordeth to perfytte men: And the other / that is to ſay ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony accordeth to imparfet men / may ful lightly gyue occaſyon to the one / that is to ſay to preſtes to be vai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne glorious / &amp; to the other that is to ſay to maryed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to myſtruſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche the ſtate of lyuenge that they be in / which neuertheleſſe vndouted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accordeth to parfyte men / and if it be well kepte / is in dede holy &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And though I knowe well that
<pb facs="tcp:19114:4"/>the meanyng of the ſayde recitale is nat that all in the one degre be ꝑfite / and in the other vnperfyte: yet for aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moche as laye men that rede it / &amp; be maried may lightly take it ſo / it may do great hurte that way / as is ſayd before / but I ſe no way howe it can do any good. And it is no doute but that matrimony in the Newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parteyneth and accordeth to par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytte men / as well as euer it dyd in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſtament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>The thyrde chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lawe of the Realme is that yf an aduowſon be voyed / and the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne preſent an able encom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bent to the ordynarye ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge to the lawe / that the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary vpon his paryll ſhall admytte hym / and if he do nat a Quare impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dit lyeth agaynſt hym / as it ſhulde do agaynſt another diſturbour. And
<pb facs="tcp:19114:4"/>yet neuerleleſſe hath the byſſhoppes and clergie made a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon / that if a preeſt haue a benyfyce / and alſo a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; dyeth / that / that ſonne ſhall nat be preſented to that benefice next after his father. And the ſeyd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytucyon is in the tytle of preeſtes ſonnes / in the fyrſt boke. And begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth: For as moche as it is forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And there is a lyke legantyne of Otho / that begynneth. Although holy fathers. &amp;c. And in that legan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne it is decreed / that if any preſtes ſonne / be immedyatly after the deth of his father / preſented to the ſame benyfyce / and no meane parſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene / that he ſhalbe depreued. And theſe lawes were made whan it was lanfull for preeſtes to haue wyues. And alſo / it maye come yet in vre / in caſe that a man haue a ſonne before his preeſthode / and after hath a bene fyce / and dyeth / in whiche caſe his ſonne is prohibyte by theſe lawes / that after the death of his father / he
<pb facs="tcp:19114:5"/>maye nat be admytted to that beny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce. And in this poynte / the lawes of the realme / and the ſayd ſpirituall lawes do vary: For in the ſame ſelfe caſe / if the patrone after the deth of the father preſente the ſonne / ſo that he be able to be preſented / if the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe refuſe hym a <hi>Quare impedit</hi> Lyeth agaynſte hym natwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge / the ſeyd conſtitucyons / and he ſhall be compelled by the kynges lawes to admytte him. And the aby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lytie or non abilytie / in this caſe ſhal be taken accordynge to the qualytie of the perſon preſented in vertu and connynge / and nat accordyng to the lawes made by the clergye. For if they wolde make a lawe / that none ſhuld be admitted to a benyfyce / but he were a maiſter of arte. That law ſhulde nat bynde in this realme / and this inconuenyence may folowe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche lawes / that if a man in ſuche caſe be admytted by auctorite of the kynges lawes / and be in poſſeſſyon / 
<pb facs="tcp:19114:5"/>the clergy wyl make proces agaynſt him / and depreue him / &amp; ſo that the one law doth the other will auoyde / where vpon variaunce and vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe may enſewe / nat onely in thoſe caſes / but alſo in other lyke / and a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke lawe is in the tytle of othes in the ſeconde boke: that begynneth thus / We determyne by this preſent ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. &amp;c. Wherby it is decreed / that the byſſhoppe ſhall receyue an Othe of him that is preſented / that he hath neither promyſed nor gyuen ought for that preſentacion vnto the preſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / neither made any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him for it / ſpecyally if he that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſeme lykely to be ſuſpected ther of / and there vpon it foloweth / that if ſuch an inconbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t refuſe to be ſworn Wherfore the ordynary for his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyence refuſeth him: That a Qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re impendit lyeth agaynſt the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary by the Kynges lawes / and he ſhalbe compelled to admit him: But than wyll the byſſhoppe for his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyence
<pb facs="tcp:19114:6"/>pretende to depreue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / &amp; grudges / ſuetes / and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunces may encreſe / and the cauſe of all this hath reſyn by reaſon that the byſſhoppes whan they ſawe cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable (as they thought) to haue la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes made in the caſe before reherſed wold nat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne to the ꝑlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue it reformed there but wold ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke lawes themſelues / which thei had none auctorite to make / and if they had complayned to the parlyament / and the parliament wolde nat loke vpon the matters / than were the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaryes the more to be excuſed: for that they dyd that in them was / and therfore as me ſemeth the parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dyd well if they wolde make lyke lawes in the caſes before reherſed / and in other lyke / where the clergy haue made lawes vpon a reſonable conſyderation / where they had none auctorite ſo to do. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawes ſhulde ſtande in good ſtrength in the lawes of the realme againſt the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / 
<pb facs="tcp:19114:6"/>as they do nowe in the ſpirytual lawe / and if it be thought that no profet can come of the makyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of / than it wyll be better to repelle them / than to ſuffre them contynue any lenger.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>The fourth chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Conſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutyon in the tytle of othes in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond boke / whiche begineth: <hi>Euenir et infra.</hi> &amp;c. Wher by it is decreed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan prelates and eccleſiaſtycal iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges enquere of the defautꝭ and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; of their ſubiectes that deſerue pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhement that the laye ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelled (if nede requyer) by ſentence of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacyon to gyue an othe to ſay the truth / and that if any with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or let the othe to be gyuen / that he ſhalbe brydeled with the ſentence
<pb facs="tcp:19114:7"/>of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacyon and interdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / and this conſtitutyon ſtandeth nat with conſcience / for it excepteth nat that there ſhall be any monicyon gyuen before accordynge to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / &amp; ouer that there be many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that a lay man may knowe / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he may nat with conſcience vtter to none other / neither after monicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor before / and yet by this conſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tucyon he ſhall be enforced therto or be a curſed / &amp; put him ſelfe in ieopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be taken as to the worlde / as a man a curſed / and yet be nat a curſed before god / and the conſtitucyon is nat / that it ſhal be diſcloſed ſecretely to the prelate / as it may be ſomtyme if the denouncer thynke the prelate ſecrete and charitable / but it muſt be done in the courte / ſo that proceſſe ſhalbe made vpon it / and that may do great hurte / for accordyng to the myndes of many doctours / ſome per ſons refrayne to offende for feare of infamye / whiche if they perceyue
<pb facs="tcp:19114:7"/>them ſelfe openly fallen in to it / wyll fall to ſine / all feare ſet a parte. And ouer that it may be / that none kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater but he only / &amp; than his ſayenge is no ſuffycyent profe / &amp; to compell him to ſwere where his othe ſhall do no good / but happely tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne him ſelf to trouble / ſemeth nat rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable. And ouer that / the othe that is apoynted to be taken by the ſayde conſtitution / is nothyng lyke to the othes that men be compelled to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke at the come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law / to enquere vpon tranſgreſſours / for they enquere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly vpon murthers / felonyes / treſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſes of landes and goodes / comen nuſances / or other thynges as be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the peace / and to the hurte of the comen welth / &amp; that requyre alſo the iugement of deth / reſtitution to the partyes / auoydyng to the comen nuſances or ſuche other as iuſtyce requyreth to be done / and that can nat be holpen by no monycyon made after the offence: And alſo ſuche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queryes
<pb facs="tcp:19114:8"/>at the comen lawe haue ben alway vſed by a generall cuſtome of the realme / for the mayntenaunce of iuſtice and of the comen welth. But this othe was brought vp by the cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gye without aſſente of the kynge or of the people / and where vnto they could nat compelle any man before: and if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll ſay that this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon may do hurte / as to auoyde cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rections / and gyue boldeneſſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be yuell to offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / to that I wyll ſay thus. I wyll nat denye but that charytable corrrcetions be ryght ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ſpecyally where there is dout of recydiuatyon &amp; fallyng agayn to ſynne / but ſurely I haue nat herde but that offenders in tyme paſte / by one meanes or other (I knowe nat redily howe) haue ben ſuffred to ſyt ſtyll without correction / nat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng all the othes that haue ben made in ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in tyme paſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:8"/>
            <head>The fyfth chapiter</head>
            <p>THere is a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon in the fyrſte boke in the tytle of the Archepreeſt / that begynneth. <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia ſacerdotum et infra.</hi> Wherein amonge other thynges the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes be recyted / and it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth therin / that the fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of the ſecond table / is to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our father and mother tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and ſpiritually / and it is ſayd after in the ſame place / that in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is nat vnderſtande onely the father and mother carnall and temporall / but alſo ſpirituall: So that the father ſpyrytuall is the prelate of the churche / mediat or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mdyeate / and the ſpirytuall mother is the churche / whoſe ſonnes be all &amp; euery catholyke perſone &amp; perſones / by whiche Conſtitucyon / ſome ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall men haue <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>tended in tyme paſt that euery man is as moche bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to honour his ſpirituall father / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by they vnderſtande his prelate and
<pb facs="tcp:19114:9"/>his ſpirituall mother / wherby they vnderſtand the church / that is to ſay preſtes / as they be to honour theyr father and mother carnall / and that if nede requyre / they be bounde to releue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temporally / as theyr own father and mother / And that is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyke to the errour of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes whiche taught the people / that if they wolde offre to the Temple / it ſhulde diſcharge them of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to their father and mother / as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth. Luc. xv. It is alſo a great ouerſyght / that the clergye calleth the churche the ſpirituall mother to euery catholyke perſone / meanynge only by that worde church / preſtes: for all Catholyke people make the churche / which is the ſpirytuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / ſo that preeſtes be but onely a parte of it: How be it that they be in dede a right notable parte therof / but to call them ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole churche it ſemeth a gret ouerſyght / and that they haue do ſo / it appereth in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:19114:9"/>writynges / as whan it is ſayde: that ſuche a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or ſuche / is againſt the lybertye of the churche / the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng is / that it is only agaynſte the lybertye of the clergye / and ſo it is where it is ſayde: that all they that wrongefully witholde any thynge from the churche be accurſed / &amp; that maner of writynge is founde in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of the Conſtitucyons and other writynges alſo: Inſomoche that in the very ſtatutꝭ of the realme that terme church, is ſomtyme vſed for the clergye / as in the ſtatute of Magna carta: the fyrſte chapiter. Where it is ſayd / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chyrch of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande ſhall haue all her olde lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes / whereby is ment no other / but that the clergye of Englande ſhalt haue their lybertye / And it is nat to thynke but that tho wordꝭ were / put in to the ſtatute by the ſpecyall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng on of the clergye / And this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner writyng cauſeth ſome of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye of Englande to exalte them ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:19114:10"/>farre aboue lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / bicauſe they thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they only be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the church / wherfore it ſemeth it is expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng in of mekeneſſe to ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall men / that / that terme church be nat from hens forth vſed only for the clergye / but that there as it hath ben vſed to be ſayd: It is agaynſte the lybertie of the church / to ſay here after that it is againſt the lybertie of the clergye or of preeſtes / &amp; that they that witholde the dutye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergie do offende againſt the clergye &amp; nat generally to ſay that they offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the churche / in which worde be compriſed al chriſten people.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>The ſixte chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a ryght troublous thynge to the people / to haue two powers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the realme / whereby they may be ſued for one thynge in ſeuerall courtes and by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall auctorities / and great expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:19114:10"/>and vnquietnes to the people ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue enſued thereby in many places / &amp; one great hurte in that behalfe maye lyghtly ryſe by reaſon of a Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon that is in the ſeconde boke / in the tytle of Iugementes. And it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth. <hi>Item omnes illi et infra.</hi> Wherby amonge other thinges / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I paſſe ouer for ſhorteneſſe. It is decreed / that the vyolatours and diſturbours of the immunitye and ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bettyes of the churche. That is to ſaye / that all ſuch ſeculer perſons as at any tyme here after ſhall preſume to withdrawe any thynge out of the houſes or other places of Archebyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes byſſhoppes / or any other ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons agaynſt the wyl of the lordes or of them that be depu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted kepers of the ſame / may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented in the place where ſuche treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas is done: Although they can nat be there founde / and a ſpecyall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is ordeyned in the ſame conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / agaynſte them that can nat be
<pb facs="tcp:19114:11"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: and it is decreed forther / that all the ordynaries and iuges of the ꝓuynce of Canterbury ſhall in ſuch caſe helpe the one an other without any dyficultye in ſpedyng of citacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons and executyons of the ſame / and all other laufull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in that behalf. And though the ſayde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon ſeme to meane non other wyſe / but that the offenders agaynſt the lybertye of the churche / and that wrongfully take awaye the goodes of the churche ſhall only be ſued: yet it maye be that by occaſyon of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true ſurmyſe / he that is innocent and no offender may be greuouſly vexed and troubled vpon it / as if a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all man take awaye wrongefully the goodes of a laye man and bryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the landes or poſſeſſyons of the churche / and after the laye man fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them there / and taketh them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / as it is lawfull for him to do / yet it maye be ſurmyſed that he offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the ſayd conſtitucyon / ſo that the
<pb facs="tcp:19114:11"/>ꝓces ſhal go forth as ſtraytly agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt him / as it ſhuld do agaynſt him that were a very offender / and there is a legantine of Octobon / that begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. For the ſauegard &amp;c. that is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of the ſame effecte as the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is: For it is / that if a man violently or enuiouſly carye awaye other mens goodes / whiche arlayed vp in holy place / or ſhall helpe / coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayll / or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſente therto / ſhalbe wrapte in the dede doynge in the bandes of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication: from the whiche he ſhall in no wyſe be aſſoyled / but he fyrſt make ſatiſfactyon to the church whiche he hath ſo greatly iniuryed: And alſo to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hathe ſuffred loſſe and domage. And that if ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate perſon moniſſhed by his dyoceſan do nat ſatiſfye within the tyme by him appoynted / his landes ſhall be enterdit / whiche ſhall nat be releaſed before due ſatiſfaccyon. And it is certayne / that the partye maye alſo be ſued in the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges courte / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:19114:12"/>may be great vexation vnto him And though the lawe of the realme be / that if any ſuche ſute be taken in the ſpirytuall courte for any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thynge / that as well the iuge as the partie re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne therby into the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munire. Yet for as moch as ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re man maye be ſued there: that is nat able to ſue a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>munire / it ſemeth more reſonable / clerely to breke the ſayde conſtytucyon and legantyne / than to ſuffre them to ſtande any len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger / for as longe as they ſhall be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſtande / ſome ſpyrituall men maye hapely thynke / that the ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Iuriſdiccion is greatly wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged / in that they maye nat be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And ouer that / ſome men thinke the ſayd conſtitucyon to be more par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyall and the leſſe indifferent / bycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that all the proces therof is made agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt ſeculer perſones. For though ſpyrituall men offende in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre of offence / as the ſeculer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth yet the conſtitucyon gyueth no ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:19114:12"/>ſpecyall proces agaynſte hym. And alſo if a man take goodes wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fro a pore man / the offence is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly greater agaynſte god / than if he toke them from any of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye / and yet no remedye is prouided for the poore man. But the clergye is in ſuche lawes highlye regarded / and that in ſuch a ſynguler and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall maner / that many of the tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raltye thynke / that they force but lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell / how pore lay men be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deled ne what wronge they haue / ſo that they haue none them ſelfe,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The ſeuenth chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anye lawes and decrees haue ben made / affermi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that it is nat lawfull that anye preeſt ſhulde be put to anſwere before laye men. And gret cenſures of excommunicatyons be made agaynſt theym that doo it. And accordyng to the ſayde decrees / 
<pb facs="tcp:19114:13"/>there is a conſtitucyon in the ſeconde boke / in the tytle of a competent cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te: and it begynueth. It happeneth ſome tyme. &amp;c. Where it is recyted / that clerkes / although they be nat ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the dede doynge / or conuicted as euyll doers / or ſuſpected of crime or treſpace / or wronge doyng to any man. Be neuertheleſſe taken by the laye power / without any regarde of perſones / &amp; be layde in pryſon. And if they can nat be founde / that than they be baniſſhed the realme / wherbi is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be outlawed. And it is ſayd there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therin the lybertie of the church is confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; broken / whan a clerke is iuged of a laye iuge / and it is therfor decreed / that if the clerkꝭ that be ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; be honeſt / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as well the takers as the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders of them ſhalbe declared exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and the landes of the takers and retayners of them to be enterdit tyll they be delyuered / and conuenient ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfaction and amendes made / but it
<pb facs="tcp:19114:13"/>is here to be noted / that the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydereth nat / that it is as law full for iuges to here the complaynte agaynſt them that be innocent / as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte theym that be gyltie / tyll the matter be tryed. And therfore if the complaynte be made of ſuch matters as they ought nat for to be delyuered to their ordinaries in / if they were gyltie / than the ordynaries may nat complayne / though they be nat dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uered where they be nat gyltie tyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter be tryed / for it is nat yet kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen whether they be gyltye or nat. And alſo / if it be in caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ought to haue priuelege and be delyuered / yet if they be aſked of offycers that haue no power to delyuer them / ther is no cauſe why ſuch offycers that ſo deteygne them / ſhulde be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycate / or their landes enterdyted. And therfore it ſemeth / that conſtytu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon farre vnreaſonable in that poin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. And that clerkes ought nat to be put to anſwere before laye men / I ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:19114:14"/>ſawe any auctoryte therof / but lawes of their owne makyng which be therin of no ſtrengh for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this realme / excepte certayn lybertyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that behalf / by the kyng &amp; his ꝓgenytours / &amp; by the lawes and cuſtomes of the Realme / whiche be right great &amp; moch fauourable vnto them / it they be well loked on. And if they wyll nedes clayme ſuche lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes by other waies / than by the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and his lawes / that they haue them of: they deſerue the leſſe to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any lenger. Than the ſeyde Conſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion ſaith farther in the later ende / That if clerkes reſtored to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / be amerced by the ſeculer iuge / for any perſonall tranſgreſſyon / the prelates ſhall nat compell the ſayde clerkes to paye the ſame amerciame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeynge they were nat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned by their own iuges. And ſurely there is no cauſe / why a clerke for a perſonall tranſgreſſyon ſhulde nat be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to pay the amercyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and that
<pb facs="tcp:19114:14"/>by the kynges Iuges as well as any laye man ſhulde / without ſpekynge any thynge to the prelates in it: but yet as longe as ſuch lawes ſtande vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>repelled: it wyl be thought by many of the clergye that it is nat ſo / &amp; that the lybertye of the churche is greatly offended by it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>The eyght chapiter.</head>
            <p>THere is a Conſtitucion in the ſeconde boke in the tytle of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t courte / that begynneth / <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpecte agatis et infra</hi> / wherin be dyuers artycles which be put in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner worde for worde among the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this realme / whiche the ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the lawe of this Realme haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly amonge them / and there is ſet as for a tytle of the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on theſe wordꝭ folowyng. Certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngꝭ anſwers. &amp;c. whiche neuertheleſſe as I ſuppoſe were neuer take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the kyngꝭ an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres / for they be in ſome poyntes
<pb facs="tcp:19114:15"/>clerely agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the lawes of this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / as it is in that there is recyted therm that prelates / for fornycacyon auowtry / or ſuche other / enioyne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metyme corporall punyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ſome tyme pecunarye / but I neuer herde that prelates haue auctoritie to enioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne peyne pecunarie for aduowtrye / fornycacion / or ſuche other. And alſo in the ſayd conſtitucyon it is ſayde / that if the prelate or aduocate of any churche aſke of the perſone any penci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on due to him / that all ſuche pency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ought to be aſked in the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all court / and maketh no exception of no maner of pencion / &amp; the lawe of the realme is clere / that Annuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teis and pencyons that begyn by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſycion or agrement of the parties / and alſo by preſcripcyon: belong to the kynges court / and therfore many haue ſayd / that the ſayde treatyſe of Circumſpecte agatis is no ſtatute / but that it was ſo named to be by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prelates / and ſo it is ſayd that it was
<pb facs="tcp:19114:15"/>in the .xix. yere of kynge Edwarde the thirde in a writ of Annuitie / and if it be ſo / than is it but onely a bare conſtitucyon / And than it is to the two poyntꝭ afore reherſed clerely voi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / becauſe it is therin dyrectely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the kynges lawes &amp; his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatyf / &amp; was alſo made without his aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or any of his ꝓgenitours.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>The nynth chapiter.</head>
            <p>THere is a conſtitucyon in the thirde boke among the conſtitucyons <hi>De Clericis non reſidentibus</hi> that begi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Audiſtis et infra</hi> wherin it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that whan a preeſt taketh two benefices with cure of ſoule without a pluralitie / that ſome lawes ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all haue iuged both to be voyde / and ſome haue holden the laſte to be voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / as the legatyne of Octobon doth: And than the ſayd Conſtitucyon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeth that he ſhalbe content with the
<pb facs="tcp:19114:16"/>laſt benyfyce ſo optayned. But all thoſe lawes / as it ſhulde ſeme by the ſayde conſtitucyon / are to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand only of ſuch benefyces / as any parſone had at that tyme withoute pluralitie. And therfore the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitution gothe farther / and decreeth that who ſo euer henſforthe receyue many benefyces: all hauyng cure of ſoules / or otherwyſe uncompatyble / without the popes diſpenſatyon / or gete them by waye of inſtitutyon or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendam / or of cuſtody / otherwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe than the conſtytution of Gregorie made in the counſaile of Lions doth permytte: the ſame in ſo doyng to be depriued from all benefyces that he hath ſo optayned. And than as I take it / the lawe of this Realme is / that all benefyces ſo optayned with out pluralitie / be clerely voyde with out any depriuation: For there be in the lawes of Englande / fyue cauſes of a voydaunce of a benifyce. That is to ſaye: Reſygnation / dethe / de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation
<pb facs="tcp:19114:16"/>/ creation / &amp; ceſſyon, And Creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is / where a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers benifices is made a biſſhop: for than all his benifeces by that creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be forchwith voyde. And where a man taketh two benifyces / without pluralytie they be voyde alſo. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called Ceſſyon. And if there muſt be therupon a depriuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before they be voyde / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the depriuation the cauſe of the voydau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; not the Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there ſhuld be but four cauſes of a voydaunce / howbeit I wyll nat determynatly ſpeke in that matter / for they that be lerned in the lawes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> realme can beſt determin whether it be ſo or notte. And if the lawe of the realme be therin as I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſayd / than can it nat be cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged by no conſtytucyon And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if the lawe be as I haue ſayd before / it foloweth therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo / that if a man take two benifyces without a pluralytie / that both be forthwith voyde. But if he than take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde / that is nat voide
<pb facs="tcp:19114:17"/>For the two fyrſte were none of his / whan he toke the thirde: But if he after take the fourthe / than are the thyrde and the fonrth voyde alſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The tenth chapitre.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lawe of the Realme is that whan a benefyce falleth voyde / and the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tron preſenteth an able &amp; a mete clerke to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynary / that the Ordynary is boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vpon the payne of a <hi>Quare impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> / and to be taken as a dyſturber / to admytte that clerke ſo preſented / in as conuenyent tyme as he may / with out any notable delaye. And yet it is decreed by a conſtitucyon / that is in the thirde boke / in the tytle of clerkes that be non reſydent. And it begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: <hi>Cum ſecundum apoſtolum</hi> et <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra.</hi> That the biſſhop in no meanes ſhall dyfferre aboue two monethes to admyt him that is preſented / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:19114:17"/>it appereth that the meanynge of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion is / that he ſhuld haue power ſo longe to delaye the prſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / if he wyll / and that is dyrect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the lawe of the realme: for he is bounde to preſente ſuche an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combent in as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient tyme as he can all notable delayes ſet aparte as is aforeſayde.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The eleuynth chapiter</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a byſſhop / abbot / pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our / or any other ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all man that hath tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall poſſeſſyons / wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeu any of the ſeyd poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyons / there is an ordre ſet by the kynges lawes / vnder what maner that Alyenation ſhall be made.</p>
            <p>And if an alyenation be made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to that ordre / it ſhall be good &amp; perfite for euer. And none other hath power to make any lawe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary therof: And yet there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:18"/>made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde boke / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in the tytle of gyftes of preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / &amp; it begynneth: That the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches indempnyties. &amp;c. Wherby it is decreed that no Abbot / or Pryor / no Archedeacon or Deane / ne any other inferior clerke / <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſume to ſelle / pledge or morgage / or to gyue in fee of new or any other wyſe to alyenat the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyons or profyttes of dygnytie / or churche that is commytted to theym / the forme and maner of the Canons therin nat obſerued / and that if any dare do the contrarye to this / bothe the thyng that is done ſhall be of no value / and alſo he that doth it ſhalbe depreued by his ſuperiour / excepte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll cal backe agayn that he hath alyenat withi a tyme prefyxed by his ſuperiour / and the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion goth yet ferther &amp; ſayth: And he alſo that herefater receyueth the churche goodes and after he is warned preſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to witholde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe ſtryken with the ſwerde of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icacion: And
<pb facs="tcp:19114:18"/>in no wyſe ſhall he be heled of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de tyll he haue made reſtitucion: All which lawes be dyrectly agaynſt the kynges <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>rogatyf &amp; the lawes of the Realme / wherfore it were better that they were put awaye / than to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to ſtande any lenger / as though they were of effecte / and be nat ſo in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The twelfth chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue goodes and take a huſbande / all the goodes that ſhe hath at the daye of Martage<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ar her huſbandes. In ſo moche that if ſhe after that / make a wyll and dye / that wyll after the lawes of the realme is clerely voyde. And if ſhe aſke lycence of her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to make a wyll / and he wyll none gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue / he offendeth nat. But if a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue goodes as an executryce / and take a huſbande / thoſe goodes
<pb facs="tcp:19114:19"/>be nat the huſbandes. But he ſhall haue them to the vſe of the fyrſt wyl. And if the wyfe in that caſe / by the lycence of her huſbande make a wyll and appoynt another to be her execu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour and dye / that wyll is good / and that executour ſhal haue thoſe goods fro the huſbande. And ſhall haue all accyons as executour of executrice to execute the fyrſte wyll / and alſo if a man be bounde to a woman by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blygacyon in an hundreth poundes / and after ſhe taketh a huſbande / and ſhe by the lycence of her huſband ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or any other her exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cutoure that wyll is good / and he or they ſo made executours ſhall haue an accyon vpon that oblygacyon: And if no ſuche wyll had ben made / the huſbande ne no nother ſhuld nat haue hadde any action vpon that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygation / vnleſſe they take a letter of adminiſtration: as adminiſtratours to the wyfe. And than there is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon made in the third
<pb facs="tcp:19114:19"/>boke / in the tytle of Teſtamentes. which begineth: Callyng to mynde the ſtatute. &amp;c. Wherby all they be ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curſed / that let the fre makyng of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentes / of aſcriptis / and of other perſones of ſeruyll condicyon. And of women alſo / both maried and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maryed / or of their owne wyfes / or of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wyues. And all that conſtitucyon / as to women couerte that haue no goodes / but as before appereth / is clerely voyde &amp; againſt the lawes of the realme. And alſo of villaynes / the lawe is, that if the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de make a generall ſeaſer of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of his vyllayne / that all the vyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laynes goodes be his. And of that it foloweth that the wyll as to tho go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des is voyde / and that neither there cutoure nor ordinarie may nat waſt any of tho goodes for prouyng of the teſtament. But if he were an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour / or if his lorde made no ſeaſer / than he might laufully make a wyll and the wyll were good: But if ther
<pb facs="tcp:19114:20"/>be ſuche a ſeaſer / the wyll is voyde and of none effecte: And than if the vyllayn haue none other goodes / the wyll is voyd and nedeth no probate.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xiii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be diuers good la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and Canons made whiche nede nat here to be reherſed / whereby it is appoynted howe the goodes of the clergie ſhall be dyſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in charitable vſes after their deth And there be but fewe caſes where a clerke after tho lawes ſhulde make a wyll. And the lawe of the realme is / that clerkes may make their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les as lyberally as any lay man may and that though they haue theym for their ſpirytuall miniſtratyon. And the conuocacyon perceyuynge the fauour that the lawes of the realme beareth to clerkes in that behalf / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ordeyned that byſſhoppes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19114:20"/>Eccleſiaſticall Iuges of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynce of Cauntorburye / ſhall in no wyſe by any crafte or colour / medle with the goodes of clerkes benefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced / whiche maye by the cuſtome of Englande make theyr teſtamentes, but ſhall ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> executours of their teſtamentes / frely to diſpoſe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame. And the ſeyde Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucyon is in the thirde boke / in the tytle of teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. And begynneth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ita quorundam et infra.</hi> And if the ſeyde Conſtitucyon / and the lawe of the realme alſo in that poynte were refourmed / And that it were appoin ted / that the goodes of clerkes ſhuld be charttably diſpoſed aff their deth ſpecially ſuche as they haue by anye ſpirituall benifyce / in ſuche maner as ſhuld be thought co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient by parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and conuocation. It ſhulde ſeme to be a good charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dede.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:21"/>
            <head>¶ The .xiiii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T apppereth ſo euy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dently in ſcripture / both in the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and in the new that the people are bownde to fynde to their ſpirytuall miniſters a ſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t porcyon of their goodes to lyue with that it nedeth nat to expreſſe here any certane auctoritye therof / and for a recompence of that certayn porcion / it is vſed in this Realme in maner vniuerſally / that the peple ſhall pay to their ſpiritual miniſters the tenth parte of their encreaſe / which tenth parte many ſpirituall miniſters clay me to be due to theym by the lawe of god. And therfore it is ſayde in the third boke / in the tytle of tythes and oblatyons / that they that paye the eleuynth ſhefe for the tenth / diſpyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the olde and new teſtament / the whiche pretence exclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth all cuſtomes and preſcriptions that mighte be had contrary to the
<pb facs="tcp:19114:21"/>tenth parte. And ſyth it is well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen / that it hath ben in late tyme / &amp; alſo yet is in queſtion and in doute: whether the tenth parte be grounded vpon the lawe of god / or vpon the lawe of man. It ſemeth that good charitie wolde / that for the clerynge of the conſcyence of many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / it ſhul de be clerely and plainly determyned whether it be ſoo or nat. And if it can be proued to be a morall lawe of the olde Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / or to be aſſigned by any authorite of the Newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / that the tenth parte ſhulde be payde / I truſt no man wyll reſyſt it. And if it can nat be proued that the tenth parte is by the lawe of god tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of very ryght the olde reſonable cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of payeng of tythes muſte be obſerued / as well by theym that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke tythes / as by them that pay them / and than if any man wyll denye to paye his predyall tythes after the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de cuſtome / or that any curate wolde eſke any more than right requireth / It
<pb facs="tcp:19114:22"/>ſemeth reaſonable that he be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſed by compulcyon of lawes to ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe the cuſtom. Howbeit ſome lawes ſeme nat reaſonable of payenge ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes: That is to ſaye: that tythe ſhul de be payed of the ſkynnes of the ſhe pe that dye to the loſſe of the owner ne yet that the tythynge of the odde lambes or calues ſhulde be ſet ouer tyll another yere / to the entent the cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate in the ſeconde yere maye haue a tenth lambe or calfe / that in the ſame yere coulde nat haue had it. Alſo it ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth a very ſore lawe that ſeruantes ſhulde tythe for their wages / or that any man ſhulde be ſewed for preuy tethes / which lyeth nat in outwarde profe / though it be rightgood to pay ſuche preuy tythes / as conſcience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. And yet it ſemeth to be the moſte ſtraunge lawe of all the other / that Perſons / vycars / and paryſſhe preeſtes / ſhall vpon a payne be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to ſewe for tythes / &amp; that they may natſyt ſtyl if they lyſt / and that
<pb facs="tcp:19114:22"/>is by a conſtitucion in the third boke that begynneth: For ſo moche as through dyuers cuſtomes. &amp;c. And all the other artycles before reherſed appere in the Conſtitucyons in the tytell of Tythes and Oblacyons: Nat all in one peragraf / but in ſeue rall peragrafes / as to the reder wyll appere / and if they were reformed it ſemeth it were a good dede: Alſo to bere the people in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the tenth parte is due to curates and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mynyſters by the immediat lawe of god / and it nat ſo / is a great offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce for it is an affyrmaunce of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth / and many perſones haue ben compelled therby to paye the tenthe parte / contrary to the olde cuſtome vſed in thoſe parties where the cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hath had ynow beſyde / wherfore it ſemeth better &amp; the more charytable way for the miniſters of the churche to confeſſe if the truth be ſo that the .x parte is grounded only vpon the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome &amp; law of man / &amp; that it began
<pb facs="tcp:19114:23"/>by the good aſſent of the people / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to clayme the .xx. ꝑte to be due to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Immediat lawe of god / and yet vnder that pretence a lawe is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in the ſayd tytle of tythes &amp; obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions / whiche begynneth: All be it god hath promyſed. &amp;c. Wherby it is decreed / that tythes ſhalbe payed generally of wode / &amp; that is agaynſt a ſtatute of this realme / made in the xlv. yere of the reigne of kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the thyrde / wherby it is enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / that a phibicion ſhall lye where a man is impledid for tythe of wode of the age of .xx. yere / by the name of <hi>Siluacedua</hi> / As it had done in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me paſt / and it ſemeth nat good to ſuffre a Conſtitucion to ſtand ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly agaynſt a ſtatute / but it be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declared why it ought ſo to do.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xv. chapiter.</head>
            <p>IT is a daungerouſe thynge to fall in to the Cenſures of the churche / and therfore they wolde nat
<pb facs="tcp:19114:23"/>be gyuen but for great cauſes. And in ſuch playne and open maner / that euery man that wolde with dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce take hede to it might knowe whether he offended in that thynge that they were gyuen for or nat: but the more pytie is / the cenſures of the churche be many tymes extended in ſuch a ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall maner / and in ſo many caſes / that no man can well knowe howe to eſchewe them / and that appereth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tymes in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions / as wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men be a curſed for breakynge of the churches lyberties / and ex<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſſeth nat what the liberties be. And in the ſaid tytell of tithes and oblations / in the later ende of the conſtitution / which begynneth. Men are ſo blynded. &amp;c. Is this generall lawe made / that all and ſynguler / ſuch as worke wicked inuentions and deceytes / by the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the rightes or the aprobate cuſto mes / or the lyberties of the church be in any thynge dimyniſſhed / or ſuffre any iniury / domage / or grefe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:19114:24"/>to the churches lybertie / ſhall be wrapped in the bonde of the great ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatyon / their abſolucyon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſpecially to their dioceſan / the poynte of deth onely excepted. And in a conſtitucion which is in the fifth boke / in the tytle <hi>Contra grauamina</hi> &amp;c. And begynneth: <hi>Cum malum et infra.</hi> It is recyted / that all they be acurſed that do maliciouſly preſume to take away fro chirches their right or through malyce / or contrarye to iuſtyce do intende to breake or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourbe the lybertyes of the ſame / and than there vpon the makers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid lawe ſay farther thus / wherby ſaye they / we perceyue all them to be tyed in the daunger and in the bonde of excomunicacyon / that obtayne let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters fro any laye courte to let or hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ꝓces of ſpirytuall iugꝭ in all ſuche cauſes as hy the verdicte of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Cannons be knowen to appartay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to the iuges of the ſpiritual court / and the ſayde letters are to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande
<pb facs="tcp:19114:24"/>as it ſemeth of the kinges pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hibycions. And who can haue know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege what parteyneth to the ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall courte by the Canons / whiche be ſo many &amp; ſo great in nombre that fewe canne come to the knowlege of them. And theſe lawes be ſo vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne that it wyll be harde for anye man / to knowe whether he be in the danger of them or nat / And where ignoraunce ſhall excuſe hym that is ſo accurſed / and where nat it is a right great doute / and ſuch thynges as touche the people ſo nygh as ſuch excomunicatyons doo / wold be brought as nigh as reaſon could dryue it in to a more clere knowledge / than thei be yet as me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xvi. chapiter</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:25"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of this Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / that if a man recouer his preſenteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. in a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re impedit / In the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges courte agaynſte a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that claymeth the patronage.</p>
            <p>And a gaynſt his incumbent / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> playntyffe ſhall haue a writte to the biſſhop to admytte his clerke / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the incumbent of the diſturbour be admytted before the writ come or nat: vpon the payne of a <hi>Quare non amiſit</hi> / and of making of a fyne to the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. And if the deffendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes might haue pledyd plenartye / and dyd nat / they loſte the aduauntage of it: and the clerke muſte be remoued. And yet it ſemeth that there is a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon made to the contrary therof in the thirde boke / and in the tytle of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tronage / whiche begynneth: Whan one optaineth in the kinges lawe &amp;c. For it is ſayde there / that if ſuche a writte come to the biſſhoppe / and the benifyce be nat voyd / that the prelate
<pb facs="tcp:19114:25"/>for his excuſe ſhall ſhewe vnto the kynge or his Iuſtices / that by cauſe ſuch benifyce is nat voyde that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat fulfyll the kinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And certayne it is that / that is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in the lawes of the realme. And than the ſayde Decree: ſomwhat to ſaue the tytle of the Playntyfe / as it thynketh / gothe further and ſaythe: that it ſhalbe lefull to the patrone in that caſe to preſent the poſſeſſoure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / that by that meanes / the title of the patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath optayned / may be declared more playnly after: But howe can the patron preſent the ſame poſſeſſour agayne / if he may nat be remoued / as the ſeyde conſtytucyon prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth that he may nat: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he ſhulde preſent him agayne / it ſhulde be rather a confyrmatyon of his firſt preſentment / and a hurte to his owne tytle / than anye furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of it / for the poſſeſſour ſhulde haue the benifyce ſtyll by the firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſentmente / and nat by the preſentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:19114:26"/>of the patrone / &amp; ſo at the nexte tyme of auoydance / the ſame dyſturbour ſhulde by reaſon of that preſentment preſent agayne. And of that it ſhulde folowe alſo / that if a dyſturboure coulde fynde the meanes that his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combent ſhulde be admytted / that he ſhulde nat be remoued durynge his lyfe / though the right patrone reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered after in the kynges courte / and that were clerely agaynſt iuſtyce / &amp; therfore the ordinary in that caſe is bounde by the lawes of the realme / vpon his ieopardye / to amoue the clerke of the diſturbour / as is ſayde before: But if the churche be full of the preſentment of an other patrone / than of hym that the Quare impedit is brought agaynſt: Or if the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary haue preſented by laps / where he is nat named in the action as a di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſturbour / than he may laufully laye tho cauſes for his excuſe / But for the plenartie of the ſame encumbent / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt whom the accyon is brought
<pb facs="tcp:19114:26"/>he can make no excuſe / and there is another decree in the thyrde boke of lyke effecte / as the ſayd fyrſte decree is: &amp; it begynneth: <hi>Eſurientes aua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ricie &amp;c.</hi> Wherin ther be ſome thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges dyrectely agaynſt the writtes of <hi>Quare impedit</hi> / &amp; <hi>quare non admiſit</hi> / as to the reder wyll appere. And it ſemeth that it is nat good / that ſuche lawes ſhulde be ſuffred to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that be ſo dyrectly agaynſte the lawes of the Realme / ſeyng that it perteyneth to the kynge and his lawes to ordre the right of all preſentementes with in this Realme.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xvii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>IT is an olde law &amp; cuſtome of this Realme that if a felon or a murderer flee to a church &amp; aſke ſent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wary there that he ſhall haue it / and that than he ſhall remayne ther four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie dayes / and no man to be prohibit for thoſe fortye dayes to bryng him mete &amp; drinke but aft the fortie daies
<pb facs="tcp:19114:27"/>meat and drynke ſhall be prohibyte him / tyll he wyll yelde him ſelf to the kynges lawes. And he that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll brynge him any meat or drinke offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the lawe / and in the mean tyme whyle he is ſo in ſentwary: it is lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the to wnſhip where he is: to ſet ſure watche and kepynge aboute him that he ſhall nat eſcape / leſt they ſhuld be puniſſhed againſt the kinge for the eſcape. And yet in a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon prouincyall / that is in the thyrd boke / in the tytle of the churches ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. And begynneth: <hi>Porro et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra.</hi> Amonge other thinges / it is de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creed / that none ſhall be ſet to watch them that take the church or the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che yearde for ſentwary / and if there be / that as well the kepers / as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſet them there / ſhall be dryuen away in forme of lawe by the ſentence of ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>communicacyon. And the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion is further / that the churche ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende them / whom the Canons only commaunde to be defended. And all
<pb facs="tcp:19114:27"/>this Conſtitucyon is voyed bycauſe they that made it hadde no power to make it / for it was made vpon this pretence / that ſuch ſentwary is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to churches by the lawes Canon / where in dede it is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges progenytours / and the lawes of his realme / in fauour and honour of churches / and therfore it hath apper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned alwayes to the kinges lawes to determine in what caſe a man ſhal haue ſentwary in a church &amp; in what nat / and how he ſhalbe ordered wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is there / howe long he ſhall tary there / and if he wyll abiure howe he ſhall be ordered whan he hath abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / and it is dayly ſene that the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament appoynteth who ſhall haue ſuche ſentwarye / and who nat / and putteth ſome fro it as they thinke rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable: and it hath cauſed great vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quietnes / that the clergye claymeth ſuche ſentwary to be by their auctori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye / and for a good reformacyon it wolde be prohibited that they ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:19114:28"/>nat do ſo herafter. And a lyke preten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce the clergye maketh / whan a man is admytted to his clergye: for they pretende that / that priuilege of cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to them that can rede by the lawes of the Cannons. And that they be Iuges who ſhall be ſo admytted / and who nat. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſaye that the ordynarye is there preſent by auctoritye of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons / to accepte ſuch as he ſhall thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to rede as clerkes / and to refuſe them / that he thiketh do nat ſo. And whan they be admytted to their cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gye / they ſaye they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſſhops priſon as to him / by who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe fauour and power they haue their clergye. And neuertheleſſe / the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the is that they haue theyr clergie in ſuche caſes by the kynge and his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / and his Iuges ſhall determyn where a man ought to haue his cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie / &amp; where nat. For if the ordinary admytte one as a clerke that is none the kinges iuges ſhall ſet a fyne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:28"/>him / &amp; alſo ſhall gyue iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon the ptie / &amp; if the ordynary refuſe one that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuges thynke redeth as a cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke they ſhall alowe him as a clerke &amp; alſo ſet a fyne vpon the ordynary for his refuſynge / and at euery generall gaole delyuery / the ordinary vpon a payne of a fyne to be ſet vpon him by the kinges iuges is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to be ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to gyue his attendance without any warnyng / &amp; at a ſpeciall gaole dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a warnyng. &amp; whan he is in the byſſhops pryſon / the byſſhop is bounde to kepe him ſafe / &amp; nat to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre him ot make any purgatyon / but accordyng to the kynges lawes / &amp; if he do / he ſhall be punyſ ſhed for the eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cape. And if the kyng pardon him / that is ſo in the byſſhoppes pryſon / the biſſhop is bounde to delyuer him vpon the kynges pardon / whethy it appereth ſuffyciently / that he is ther by the kiges power &amp; auctority. And yet many ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all men prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary / And therfore if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter and
<pb facs="tcp:19114:29"/>other lyke were ſette in a clere waye it ſhulde cauſe greate quietnes / and thoughe they that haue their clergye haue it by the kynges lawes / as is afore ſayde / and nat by the lawe Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>non / yet are the Ordynaries bounde in conſciens to kepe them that be ſoo commytted to them for their clergie / as fauorably as they ought to do if they were brought thether by their owne auctorite.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xviii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an old lawe in this realme / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan Byſſhoppes die / the kynge ſhall haue the temporaltes during the vacacyon / &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtatutes be made how the ſame te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poralties ſhalbe ſaued fro waſt and deſtruction durynge the vacacyon / and that the kynges exchetours ſhal nat ſell the vnderwodes / ne ſhall nat
<pb facs="tcp:19114:29"/>hunt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ꝑkes or warens / nor fyſh in their fiſſhyngꝭ nor do any waſt / to the <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>iudyce of the houſes or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deane &amp; the Capitre / Prior or ſupprior / and that the Prior &amp; ſupprior maye take it to ferme if they wyll. And for as moche as in the tyme of ſuche va cacyons of Byſſhopprykes / and of abbeys and Priories / whan they be nat taken to ferme. Hurte hath come ſometyme to the ſayd poſſeſſyons by the defaulte of the kynges offycers / where vpon the newe electes myght haue good remedy by the lawe of the realme if they wolde / yet the ſpirt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtye as it ſemeth / nat contented ſo to do / but pretendynge that by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es made by them ſelfe / they wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſuffycye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t remedy without aſking any ayde of the kynge / haue made a law in that caſe as it appereth in the thirde boke in the tytle of churches lyberties / in the chapiter whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth. Where the kyng. &amp;c. which chapiter ſhall be reherſed hereafter
<pb facs="tcp:19114:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:31"/>worde for word / that euery man may ſe theffecte therof. And it beginneth thus: Whan the kynge hathe the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodye of Cathedrall or Conuentual churches / although acordinge to the chartour of lyberties grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the church by the kinge and his predeceſſours / he ought to receyue onely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne profytes and certayn ſeruyces and that without the diſtreyninge of men / and deſtruceyon of thinges. It chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth neuertheleſſe that his bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyffes through imoderate tallages &amp; exaccyons / do bothe vyolently take away the churches tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes goodes in tyme of vacation / and alſo deſtroy the parkes / woods / ſtore poles / hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / and ſcatereth the goodes abrode they euyll entreate the pore &amp; ſtretch their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des nat only to thoſe thyng; which they were wont to optayn by reaſon of cuſtody: But alſo vnto the goodes of them that remaine in lyfe / that is to wit / to that blade and ſtore &amp; ſuch other / wherwith the chapiter
<pb facs="tcp:19114:31"/>and couente ought to be ſuſtayned: Yea / and preſume to take other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges lyke wyſe / whiche by reaſon of Baronye / can in no wyſe apptayne vnto him: As tythes &amp; oblations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longinge / and apperteynig to chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches appropriate vnto byſſhoprik ꝭ &amp; monaſteries and other lyke thinges. Therfore to withſtande this euyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we ordeyne / that as ſone as the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges eſcheters &amp; baylyffes ſhall haue entred ſuch cuſtody / the prelat ꝭ whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue iuriſdiccyon / ſhall openly &amp; ſolemply forbyd all the ſeyd baylyff ꝭ generally / that vnder payne of erco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication they atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt no ſuch thig; But if they do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary / let it be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly declared / that they be fallen in to the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tcation decreed agaiſt the violatours &amp; troublers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches lyberties vntyll thei haue made a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / for the hurts &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries. which ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if they dyſpyſe after ſuch denuncyation. Let proces be made agaiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by interdiccyons
<pb facs="tcp:19114:32"/>and other penalties ordeyned aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſt ſuche wrong doers / and excepte the kynge admoniſſhed therof make competente reſtitucyon / or cauſe the thinges ſo taken to be reſtored and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mended. Let proces be made againſt hym / as it is decreed in other caſes touchynge the kynge / and the ſelfe ſame thinges which are before decre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed for the kynge and his minyſters we wyll to be obſerued in other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryour lordes / if peraduenture / the cuſtodye come to them. Thus farre goth the ſeyde conſtitucyon / wherby it appereth / that though the parties greued might in ſuch caſe haue good remedye by waye of peticyon to the kynge or againſt his bailyffes by the ordre of his lawes: that yet the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye nat content with thoſe remedyes haue taken vpon theym to make the ſeyde conſtitucyon to declare that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che offycers be nat onely fallen in to the ſentence of excomunication decre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed agaynſte the vyolatours of the
<pb facs="tcp:19114:32"/>churches lyberties / but alſo that if they make not a competent amendes that proces ſhalbe made agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by interdiction / and yet nat content with ſuche extreme lawes agaynſte offycers / they procede farther / and decre / that if the kynge him ſelfe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed make nat competent reſtytu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion / that than proces ſhalbe made agaynſt him / as is decreed in other caſes touchyng the kyng / and what an entrepryſe that is to make proces agaynſt the kynge / that ought firſte to ſewe to him by peticyon it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant / and though the ſayde lawe wyll that the kynge ſhulde be fyrſte monyſſhed / yet that monycyon can nat be taken for any ſute by peticion / but rather for a ſute by compulcion / and ſurely ſythe there be ſuffycient lawes ordeyned by parliament for a remedye in ſuche caſe / it ſemeth ſome what to be meruecyled why the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye wolde alſo make this Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / as though theyr poſſeſſyons
<pb facs="tcp:19114:33"/>had nothyng be fauored by the kyng nor his Realme / and the lawes that be made for the preſeruacion of ſuch temporaltes in the tyme of vacation without waſt or diſtruction be theſe. Fyrſt in the ſtatute of Magna carta the .v. chapiter: It is ordeyned that the Gardeyn as long as he hath the cuſtody / ſhall ſuſtayne Houſes / par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes / waters / &amp; mildames. &amp;c. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynyng to the lande of the iſſues of the ſame / &amp; ſhal yelde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the heire at his full age / enſtored w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plowes / and all other thynges at the leeſt as he receyued them / and it is farther enacted / that all theſe thyngꝭ ſhalbe obſcrued alſo / of the vacacions of Archebyſſhoppes / byſſhops / abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyes / prories / churchꝭ / &amp; dygnities that to the kyng belong / except only that thoſe dygnities may nat be ſold and that ſtatute of Magna carta is confermed by the ſtatute of Weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xxi. chapiter. And after in the .xiiii. yere of Kynge Edwarde
<pb facs="tcp:19114:33"/>the thirde / the .iiii. and .v. chapiter. It is prouided that no exchetour nor none other keper of the vacations of the temporalties / ſhall nat ſell the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derwod / nor hunt in the parkes / wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes / nor fyſſhe / ne do waſt nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the piudyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſes And that the deanes &amp; the chapiters or ſuperiour priours / or ſuppriours may take them to ferme if they wyll / ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exchetour ſhall nat medle. And this ſtatute was made at the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecyall deſyre of the clergye / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with at that tyme they wer very well content. And vpon theſe ſtatutes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons maye be taken / if they that be greued lyſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playn. And what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as though no remedy had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prouyded for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before: And to ſay the truth / I haue herde of none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath had cauſe notably to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playn in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behalf / how beit I ſpeke nat this to thentent I wold haue it appere the defaut in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kige of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion &amp; ſuch other
<pb facs="tcp:19114:34"/>to be in the prelates that nowe be / as though they wolde proces ſhulde be made agaynſt the kige / for they were nat preuy to the makynge of the ſayd Conſtitucyon. And therfore if they wyll aſſente to the refourmynge ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of / there can no defaute be aſſygned in them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xix. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a man be excommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged / and he wyll nat ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytte him ſelfe to the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / ne deſire abſolucion but wyll obſtinatly ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſtyll ſo accurſed / the ſpyrituall iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſdiccyon hath no power to do any thinge further agaynſt him. But if the partye thervpon ſtande ſtyll ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed fortye dayes / and the biſſhop certifye the kynge therof / than the cuſtome of the realme is in fauour of the ſpyrituall Iuriſdiccyon / that the kynge ſhall awarde a writte oute of
<pb facs="tcp:19114:34"/>his Chauncerye / whiche is called a writte <hi>De exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icato capiendo</hi> / which ſhalbe directed to the ſherif wher the partie is / wherby the ſheryf ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to iuſtifye him by his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye / tyll he haue made amendes to holy churche. &amp;c. And whanne he is ſo in priſone. If he by his fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es offre to the byſſhoppe ſuffycient caucyon or gage / to ſtande to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the churche / and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the lawe. And he refuſe to take it / than the lawe and cuſtome of the realme is / that the kynge ſhall ſende to the ſherif a nother writ / which is called a writ <hi>De cautione admitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundynge him therby to aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe the biſſhop to take the caucyon. And if he refuſe to take itꝭ than to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuer the partie out of priſon / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon as it appereth in the thirde bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / in the tytle of the churches lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye / in a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion that begynneth</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seculi principes. &amp;c,</hi> The clergye complayneth gretly / for that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:35"/>in that caſe ſhalbe ſo delyured / no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction made neither to the church nor to the partie and they complaine as though the eccleſiaſticall offyce were thereby confounded and made veyne / while the laye Iuges that ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue nat the keye of power &amp; knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / whiche laye men are ſo ſtraytly bounde to folowe and obeye / that the auctorite of examinacyon Iugynge and commaundyng is vtterly forbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them in all ſuche thynges as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyneth to the ſpirituall iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / and yet go they aboute as the ſayde Conſtitucyon ſayth: To cutte downe another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes corne. Where vpon it is to be noted that the lay iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of whom the Conſtitucion ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in this place are to be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the kynge him ſelfe or his chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour / for there is non other iuge in this caſe that medeleth w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the mater / and if the clergye wolde that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſhulde nat haue auctorite to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne / iuge and commaunde in this
<pb facs="tcp:19114:35"/>caſe / than their iuriſdiccion coulde go no ferther / and therfore that the kynge dothe in takynge of ſuche an excomunicat perſon / he doth it at the deſyre of the byſſhop / and whan he delyuereth him agayne accordynge to the cuſtome of his Realme / bycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the byſſhop refuſeth a reaſonable caucyon / he hath nothyng hurte the ſpirytuall iuriſdiccyon / ne taketh v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him the keyes of the power or knowlege that appteyneth to it? he yet he goth nat about to cut downe any other mans corne / for whan the partye is ſo lette out of priſon for the refuſynge of the ſayd caucyon / he is yet accurſed ſtyll as he was before &amp; ſo ſhall he ſtande / tyll he ſo demeane him ſelfe that he maye optayne his abſolucion. But if the kynge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that by that delyuery the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye ſhulde be alſo dyſcharged of his exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacyon. Than myght the clergye ſomewhat more reaſonable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliane that the Kynge medeled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:36"/>the keyes of power and knowlege / and that he cutte downe a nother mannes corne. Butte as this caſe is they haue no cauſe ſo to complayne for all that he doth in this mater con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernyng their iuriſdiccyon / is eyther to do them good / or els no hurt. And ſo it appereth / that they complayne without a cauſe / &amp; yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plainte is ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deled vnder ſuche a facyon that it might make ſom that ſhuld happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to rede it / thynke that the ſpyrituall Iuriſdiccyon were therin greuouſly offended. And yet / whan the matter is throughly loked vpon / it appereth that it is nat ſo. Alſo in the ſame Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyon / a lyttell before the clauſe that is remembred before / the ſame Conſtitucyon ſayth thus: And ſome tyme whan a ſurmyſe is made to the kynge / that the ſeyde parties impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned be excomunicated for ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as apperteyneth nat to the ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall courte / that than haue the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryffes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement / that if he
<pb facs="tcp:19114:36"/>be excomunycate and impriſoned for ſuch cauſe and none other / to cauſe the biſſhops to delyuer them ſhortly / and no credence or faithe / ſaith the ſeyde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon is gyuen to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the ſpirytuall Iuges vpon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſe of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacyons / and vpon thoſe wordes / it is to be noted / that the ſeyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clauſe miſtaketh the lawe of the realme ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye farre / for the lawe is / that ſuche an excomunicate ꝑſone ſhall neuer be put in to the biſſhops priſon / but in to the ſheryffes priſon / and than to haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſheryffe / that he ſhall cauſe the byſſhop to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer him out it ſtandeth natte with reaſon / for they can nat delyuer him oute of priſon that they haue nat the kepynge of / and as they myſtake the lawe of the Realme in that poynte / ſo they do in many other in the ſayde Conſtitucyons / as it wyll appere if they be well &amp; thorowly loked vpon / and it is ſomwhat to be meruayled / 
<pb facs="tcp:19114:37"/>that the Conſtitucyon ſayth / that no credence nor faith is gyuen to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the ſpyrituall Iuges / vpon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſes of excomunicatyon: for vpon their proces and certifycat the partie is areſted / and than if it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere after by the proces / that the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye is impriſoned for ſuche cauſe as appertayneth natte to the ſpirytuall courte / than dothe the kynge well / if he commaunde the ſheryf to delyuer him out of pryſon / and he is alſo of Iuſtyce bounde to do it. And ouer that / if a man were excomunicate for that thynge that apparteyneth nat to the ſpirytuall courte / and after ſuche a proces were ſhewed / wherby it ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de appere / that the matter ſhulde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteyn to the ſpirytuall courte / and the partye wyll auerre the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye: what credence ſhulde be gyuen to the ſpirytuall proces in that behalfe. I wyll nat take vpon me to determyne but commytte it to other / howe be it it ſhulde ſeme reſonable that the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye
<pb facs="tcp:19114:37"/>ſhuld haue auerreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t agaynſt it. And after in another Conſtitucyon / that is in the fyfth boke / in the tytle of the ſentence of excomunicatyon / &amp; begynneth: Furthermore it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſometyme. &amp;c. Amonge other thynges that be moch lyke to the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before reherſed / it is decreed that if the writte of <hi>Excomunicato capiendo</hi> be required / and in eſpecial where it ought to be awarded bi the laudable cuſtome of the realme / and it be nat graunted / that the kynge muſte be warned by the prelate / that it maye pleaſe him to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te the ſeyd writte / which if he wil nat do all his cyties / caſtels / boroughes &amp; villages whiche he hathe within that dyoces ſhalbe e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terdicted / &amp; ſo an interdiccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is deryuyed agaynſt him by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fauour that his owne law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / &amp; the cuſtome of his realme hath gyuen vnto the clergye. And I thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke veryly / that if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rulers wolde ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the payne to loke vpon the ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:19114:38"/>Conſtitucions / they wold nat ſuffre them to ſtande vnreformed / for gret charges and expences be lyke to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vpon excomunications / as long as they ſhall be ſuffred to ſtande in effecte.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xx. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a Parſon or a vycar ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre their houſes to be in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye / &amp; dye: It is reſonable that his executours ſhulde repayre them / if they haue goodꝭ ſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to do it / but yet it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpiritual iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath no power to compell the executours to make the reparacyons / for it is a thynge concernyng waſte / that is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall / and parteyneth merely to the kynges courte / and the iugement of it concerneth the payment of money by the executours / whiche the ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall court hath no power to enioyn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executour to. And if they do / they
<pb facs="tcp:19114:38"/>ronne therby in to the premunire / &amp; therfore it were better that a remedy were prouyded in ſuche caſe by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament / than that ſo great daunger ſhulde hange vpon the prelates / and alſo vpon the parties that ſhulde ſue accordinge to the Conſtitucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in that behalfe / wherof one is in the thirde boke / in the tytle of buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of churches. And begynneth If the perſone of any churche. &amp;c. And the other is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame tytle / and begynneth: We ordeyne that no <abbr>inqſicyon.</abbr> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxi. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is reſyted in a Conſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tucyon / that is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third boke / in the tytle of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches liberties / and begi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thus: For as moch as the laye be forboden. &amp;c. That lay men be forboden / as well by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of god as of man / to ordre and
<pb facs="tcp:19114:39"/>dyſpoſe the churche goodes: by the which terme churches goodes / ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall men vnderſtande / as well lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and tenementes / as chatels per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonels. And I ſuppoſe / that there is no lawe of god that dothe prohibyt laye men to dyſpoſe and determyne the right of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and goodes of the church: but that it moſt properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyneth to theym / and nat to the clergye. And that ſemeth to appere. Luc. xii. Whan our lorde refuſed to denye the enheritaunce bytwexte the two brethern. And it is to ſuppoſe / that as he refuſed to medell with the iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuche temporall matters him ſelf / that he wolde his appoſtels and diſcyples / to whom the clergye be ſucceſſours ſhulde doo the ſame. And as it ſemeth he wolde alſo that the Emperour that tyme beinge / and his lawes ſhulde doo it and nat he. Than the ſame Conſtitucyon gothe further / and fyndeth a defaute at pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhens / that take trees growynge
<pb facs="tcp:19114:39"/>in churchyeardes ſome tyme to their owne vſes / and ſometyme to the vſe of the churches. And it byndeth all ſuch doers in the ſentence of excomu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicatyon / comprehended in a lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne of Octobon / &amp; in a conſtitucion made by the counſell of Oxforde / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the vyolatour of the churchꝭ lybertye. And it decreeth further / that they ſhalbe put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the company of the faythfull / to their confuſyon &amp; ſhame / tyll they offre &amp; make an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. And this is a right ſore and an extreme lawe: for as I take it the trees in the churcheyar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ought to ſtande ſtyll for the deffen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the churche / and of the chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell as long as they may ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / with out they be felled by the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / as well of the Parſone or Vycar / as of the paryſhe / and if the Parſon or Vycar agre that the pariſſhens ſhall fell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the reparations of the churche / I thynke they do ryghte well: And if the pariſſhens agre that the Parſon
<pb facs="tcp:19114:40"/>or Vycar ſhall haue them to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paracyons of the chauncell / I thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke that they do well alſo / but if a tree in the Churcheyarde fall downe by tempeſt / or otherwyſe / who than ſhal haue the tre it is more doute / for ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon it is to ſe in whome the frehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the churcheyarde is: Howe be it the graſſe hath alwaye by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cuſtome parteyned to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Vycar / and I wyll no ferther ſpeke in that mater at this tyme / but that I thynke verily there is no caſe reaſonable / why ſo harde and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me a Conſtitucion euyn to their con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſion and ſhame that take ſuch treis ſhulde be made againſt the pariſſhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in that caſe / though they take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trees without aſſente of the parſone or vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care / ſpecyally if they take theym to the vſe of the churche.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>FEwe men maye do more good than a good precher may. and fewe men maye do more hurte than
<pb facs="tcp:19114:40"/>an euyll precher maye. And there be many lawes Canon / and alſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyons prouincyall made who ſhall haue auctoritye to preche / and who nat / which to eſchewe tedyouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the reders / I wyll omytte for this tyme / excepce onely a Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon prouincyall / that is in the fyfth boke / in the tytle of Heretykes / and Secſmarykes. And it begynneth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reuerendiſſime ſinado et infra,</hi> Wherby it is decreed / that no ſeculer or reguler nat auctoriſed by the lawe or other wyſe ſpecially priuyleged to preach the worde of god / ſhall take vpon him the offyce or vſe of prechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g excepte he fyrſt preſent himſelf to the Dyoceſan / and be founde apte and mete / and be than ſente to preach by him / and that they which afferme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe to haue ſpecyall priuylege / ſhall really exhibyt and ſhewe their priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege to the Parſone or Vycare. &amp;c. And they that pretende to be ſente by the dyoceſan / ſhall in lykewyſe ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:19114:41"/>the letter of the Dioceſan vnder his great ſeale: And than the ſayd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyon goth further &amp; ſaith thus. The perpetuall Curate / we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande to be ſente by the lawe / to the place and people of his owne cure. Natwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge / if it happen any ſuch to be ſuſpended fro ſuch prechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by the Dyoceſan / or by any other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryour for errours or hereſies / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is pretended that he hath preched affermed / or thought: than maye he in no wyſe medle with prechynge in our Dyocyſe / vntyll he haue purged him ſelf of that defaute at the iuſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterment of him that dyd ſuſpende him / and that he be laufully reſtored agayn vnto prechynge of which his reſtitucion he ſhall haue letters and cary them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in al places where he ſhall afterwarde preche / and ſhal really exhibit the ſame in maner and forme aforſayd. Thus farre is of the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion: &amp; as me ſemeth it is no reaſonable cauſe / to prohibyt any man / ſpecyally a curat that hath ben
<pb facs="tcp:19114:41"/>admytted to preach: that he ſhall nat preach for errours or hereſies / which is pretended that he hath preched / af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermed / or taught: for it may be <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man hath affermed preched &amp; alſo taught hereſies / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet it is nat ſo in dede: for euery <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>tence is nat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way true &amp; if there be no ſuch hereſie <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ched nor taught tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faut wherof he ought to pourge him ſelfe. Than the ſeyde Conſtitucyon goth yet further / and ſayth: That if any precher diſpyſe this holſome ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute / and do prech on his owne heed agayne: ſayenge obſtinatly in word ordede / declaryng that the ſeyde ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of excomunicatyon may nat be decreed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the church in the perſones of their prelates / yf they wyll nat therfore abiure / they ſhall be taken for heretykes / &amp; they: goodes to be forfayte by the lawe. &amp; ferthermore it is decreed / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye or people ſhall admytte none to prech / excepte they firſt make a profe of their auctoriſynge: And if they
<pb facs="tcp:19114:42"/>do otherwiſe / the place where the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge is / ſhall be vnder church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terditynge in the doynge. Theſe be very ſtrayte lawes. And they pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hibyt ſuche perſones to preache: as peraduenture wold preach well and catholycally / and that wolde hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely touch ſomwhat concernyng the Ordinaryes or their iuriſdictyons / whiche they wolde nat gladlye haue ſpoken of. And therfore I holde it a very neceſſary thyng for the rulers to loke well vpon this matter / to ſe it ſet in ſuch ordre / that nothyng be don agaynſt the lawe of god therin. And I ſuppoſe verily / that the rulers be bounde in conſcyence to do it / and in that the Conſtitucyon decreeth / that their goodes ſhall be forfayt / that is a voyde decre: for they had none auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritye to decree vpon any goodes. and the forfyture of the goodes / for hereſye is ordred by the ſtatute made in the ſeconde yere of kynge Henry the fyfth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:42"/>
            <head>¶ The .xxiii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is decreed in the ſeyde fyfth boke / in the tytle of heretykꝭ and ſciſmatikes / in the conſtitucion that begynneth. None maye preſume. &amp;c. That none ſhall diſpute openly or preuely of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycles determyned by the church / as they be conteyned in the decrees De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals and Conſtitucyons prouyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall or Sinodals / except it be done to haue the true vnderſtandynge of them. Ne maye call in to doute / the auctoritye of the ſame decrees Decre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tals / and Conſtitucyons prouyncyal or the power of the makynge of them And ſpecyally concernyge the adora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of the gloriouſe croſſe / worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynge of ſayntes Images or pylgrymages makynge / vnto their places and relyques: or agaynſte othes to be made after the vſed maner in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes accuſtomed in both courtes / that that is in the ſpirytuall courte and
<pb facs="tcp:19114:43"/>temporall: but that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſforth all ſhal teache comenly and preach / that the croſſe and Images of the crucyfyxe and other Images of ſayntes ought to be worſhypped in the memory and honour of them / whom they fygure and repreſent. &amp;c. And here it is to be noted / that the reſonynge and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putynge of the Artycles of the faith be nat onely prohibyte / but the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putynge of the Articles / determyned by the churche / as they be contayned in the decrees decretals and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucyons prouincyall or Synodals / &amp; prohibiteth nat expreſſely the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the Artycles of the faythe / Howbeit in that the Conſtitucyon excepteth / that a man may reaſon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thinges to haue the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge of them it ſemeth very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable: but that a man may nat call in to dout the auctoritye of the ſame decrees decretals or Conſtitucyons / or the power of makynge of theym. I ſe nat how it ſtandeth with reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:19114:43"/>or anye maner of indyfferencye / that that ſhulde be prohibyt: for there be vndoutedly many of theym that the makers had no auctoritye to make / and that be alſo dyrectly agaynſt the kynge and his prerogatyue / and no cauſe why they ſhulde be ſo / wherof ſome be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred in dyuers of theſe chapiters. And I ſuppoſe verilye / that the moſt parte of all the clergye wolde confeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf that it is ſo / if they were examyned vpon it. And as to the ſeyd Artycle / that Images ſhulde be worſhipped. I can nat per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue howe it ſhulde ſtande with the lawes of god / that the Image ſelfe ſhulde be worſhypped / howbeit the authorityes that cauſe me to ſaye ſo I wyll nat touche at this tyme. And I thynke farther that it were ryght expedyent / that chyldren whan they come to the yeres of diſcrecyon / ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be dilygently admoniſſhed / that they ſhall nat eſteme ymages in ſuch maner as they did in their childhod.
<pb facs="tcp:19114:44"/>And furthermore to ſay that he that affermeth or techeth that othes to be made vpon the holy goſpels / incaſes in the lawe expreſſed / maye nat law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be gyuen in bothe courtes of all that haue entreſt to gyue them / ſhall ronne in to the paynes of hereſie: as it is decreed there in the ſeyd Conſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tucyon that he ſhulde do / me ſemeth it can nat ſtand with the ordre of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce / for though his ſayenge therin be vntrewe / yet it is no hereſye: for it is nat prohibyt by the lawe of god to ſaye it. And vpon this poynt / that is to ſaye / that the clergie hath made thynges hereſy / that be none by the lawe of god / and that they haue put them in execucyon / haue ryſen great grudges agaynſte the clergye. And therfore if the clergye wolde decree that if a man wolde obſtynatly ſaye / that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be tenant by the curteſye in this realme / though hys wyfe were ſeaſed in fee durynge the ſpouſayls / and though they had iſſu
<pb facs="tcp:19114:44"/>or that the enheritance in this realme oughte nat to dyſcende to the eldeſt ſonne ſhulde therfore be taken as an heretyke / yet were he no heretyke in dede / though he ſayde vntrewly / for euery errour is nat hereſy. And ſo in this caſe / though a man ſayde vntru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / that none ought to ſwere / neither in the ſpirytuall court nor temporall yet were he no heretike. And I thike further / that if the clergye according to the ſeyde Conſtitucyon conuycted a man in the caſe / or the other caſes before remembred / or any other lyke of hereſy / and delyuered him to the laye courte / that the kynge might nat by his lawes grant forth his writte. <hi>De heretico comburendo,</hi> For as I take it / that writte oughte nat to be graunted but for hereſy / whereby a man falleth fro the fayth and fro the trewth of holye ſcrypture. and ouer that / what it ſhulde meane / that the ſeyd Conſtitucyon maketh it hereſy to ſay that no man aught to ſwere in
<pb facs="tcp:19114:45"/>the temporall courte. I can nat redy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly tell / but it were to the entente / that by mayntenaunce of othes in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall courtes / occaſyon might be the rather taken to mayntayne othes in ſpirituall courtes / howbeit as I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſomewhat touched in the fourth chapyter / ſome of the othes that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably be gyuen in the ſpirytuall courtes / as to enquyre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defautes and exceſſes of the people / ar vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable as I haue partly touched the cauſes in the ſeyd fourth chapiter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxiiii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Conſtitucyon in the fyfth boke / in the tytle of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſleye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / that begineth: It is inacted by prouiſyon. &amp;c. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is decreed thus: if patrones / ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocates / or Feodatories / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vicelor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / through myſcheuouſe boldneſſe preſume to ſley or meyme by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:19114:45"/>or by other / any Parſone of churche Vycare / or Clerke of the ſame chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / that they ſhall vtterly loſe patro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nage / aduocation / fee and vycelord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp which they had in the churche. And their poſterite in no wyſe ſhall be receyued in to the college of cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vnto the fourth generatyon / nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall optayne the honour of dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nytie or Prelacye in reguler houſe. And this we wyll / often tymes to be denounced in the church. Thus far goth the Conſtitucyon / which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vncertayne in it ſelfe / in ſomoche that it is harde to tell what was the very meanyng of them that made it. And if they me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as ſone as a patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ſlayne a parſone / a Vycare or a clerke in the churche / that forthwith the patronage ſhuld be forfayt / than they myſtoke the lawe of the realme very farre / for ſuch enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal neuer be forfayt by the dede / tyll Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement be gyuen vpon it. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore it is no doubte / but that of
<pb facs="tcp:19114:46"/>ſuche temporall inherytaunce / they had no power to make any ſuche la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / that it ſhulde ſo be forfayt. And if theyr meanynge were / that if he were after the ſleyng atteynted at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawe / that than he ſhulde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte the patronage: Than the Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtytucyon neded lyttell to haue ben made / for ſo he ſhulde haue done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / wherfore the Conſtitucyon is therin euery waye voyde. And to the other poynte of mayminge / it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne that though a patron mayme the Parſone / Vycare / or Clerke in a churche / that he ſhall nat forfayte the patronage / though he be therof attai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted / for there is no enheritaunce for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte by no ſuche offence. And the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me lawe that is of a patronage is of all the other thynges that be aboue ſpecifyed in the ſeyde Conſtitucyon. And than that the heyres of theym that do any ſuch act ſhal nat be recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued in to no dygnytie or prelacye of reguler houſe / vnto the fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyon
<pb facs="tcp:19114:46"/>that byndeth nat in the lawes of the realme: for if the patrone pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the heyre of them that dyd the dede / &amp; that is alſo within the fourth generatyon to a priorye preſentable of his gyfte. And the Ordynarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed bycauſe of the ſeyde Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / it is no dout, but that a Quare impedit ſhulde lye agaynſt him / and he ſhuld be admytted: And if the Or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynarie after depreued him by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſeyd Conſtitucyon / the patron might preſent the ſame ſelfe parſone agayne / and ſo ſhulde be a great con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſyon betwyxte the ſeyd lawes / and though ſuche matters be nat moche lyke to come in vre: yet to ſee ſuche thynges ſtande / wherof hurte maye come &amp; no good. I thynke it is nat good to be ſuffred / for many reders maye happely thynke it is euen as the Conſtytucyon ſpeketh / and yet in dede it is nat ſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxv. chapiter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19114:47"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon in the fifth be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / &amp; in the tytle of canonycall purga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that begineth <hi>Statuimus et infra</hi> wherby it is decre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if clerkꝭ haue made their canony<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon ſuche thynges as was layd &amp; obiecred agaynſt them / &amp; that yet neuertheleſſe the laye power taketh their goodꝭ or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holdeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that ſuch takers &amp; witholders ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled vnto reſtitucyon of the ſeid goodes by cenſures of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church. And the canonycall purgation y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in the ſeyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyon / ſemeth to be the purgation of clerkes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uycte / that be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſſhops pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and there make their purgation / and that the prelates ment at the makige of the ſeyd conſtitucyon / that if they dyd ſo / that they ſhulde haue theyr goodes that they had whan they wer conuycie. But I take the lawe of the
<pb facs="tcp:19114:47"/>realme to be / that clerke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uycte ſhal forfayte his goodes. And if it be ſo / that conſtitucyon can nat helpe it by no maner of purgatyon that can be made by the clergye.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxvi. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Relates haue done verye moch in time paſt to brige it about that clerkꝭ ſhulde nat be put to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer before lay men. And bicauſe cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes ſometyme offended in huntynge in forreſtes &amp; parkes / wherof many tymes ſuche great dyſpleaſure was taken / that amendes muſt nedes be made. The Prelates made a lawe to appoynt howe the ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſhulde be made in ſuche caſe by their owne auctoritie / ſo that there ſhuld nede no ſute be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behalfe at the kingꝭ lawe / &amp; the remedy was thys: As it appereth in the fifth boke / in the title
<pb facs="tcp:19114:48"/>of a clerke that is an hunter in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyon / which begynneth: We or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne that if any clerke. &amp;c. That if the clerke were conuycted therof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ordinary or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed it / that than the Ordinarie ſhulde make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptyon therof in his goodes / and ſatiſfye the partie greued. And if he had no goodes / that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his biſſhop ſhulde greuouſly puniſſh him. And ſurely if any Ordynarie dyd execute the ſeyde Conſtitucyon / and put the clerke to anſwere of the offence afore him / and after made redemptyon of his goodes accordynge to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyon / he ſhulde renne clerely in to the premunire. And furthermore in caſe that the clerke haue no goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / ne can nat be founde / he ſhall be outlawed at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mone lawe / nat withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge any puniſſhment that the Ordynaries coulde make vpon him. And yet it ſemeth that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſeyd Conſtitucyon wold haue preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted that outlagarie if they
<pb facs="tcp:19114:48"/>coulde. And now let euery man iuge what goodneſſe can come by the ſeid Conſtytucyon / or why it ſhulde be ſuffred to contynew any lenger / ſyth it can do no good to prelates or cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / ne to none other.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxvii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>THere is a Conſtitucyon in the fyfthe boke / and in the tytle of paynes / that begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth: <hi>Eterne ſanctio volun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatis et infra.</hi> Wherin it is recyted a monge other thinges / that it oftety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes happeneth Archebiſſhops / byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops / and other inferiour prelates to be called to ſeculer iugement / for ſuch thiges as be knowen merely to apperteyne to their offyce / and to the ſpirytuall courte: wherof I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyte parte / and parte I ſhall omytte to eſchewe tedyouſneſſe. Firſt it is recyted / that if prelates parchaunce haue amitted or nat amytted clerkes
<pb facs="tcp:19114:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:50"/>to churches vacante or nat vacante: or haue excomunicated their ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / haue enterdited / haue had cogni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of cauſes ſpirituall / as of boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of pariſſhes / which as it is ſayd there may in no wyſe pertayne to the ſeculer courte / or if they haue taken examinacion of the defaultes of their ſubiectes as of partury / promes bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng / troublynge of the churche ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties / ſeynge that the violatours therof be by the ſentence made vpon the kynges charter excomunicate in the dede doyng: or if they holde plee bytwyxt the laye complaynyng and Clerkes defendynge in perſonall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons vpon contractes or as contrac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / vpon treſpas or as treſpas. All which matters w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuers other here omitted is prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded there in the ſayd Conſtitucion to be mere ſpirytuall / and I haue here recyted theſe arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles therof / that it maye the better ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pere whether they be mere ſpirituall or nat / And it is euydent ynow that
<pb facs="tcp:19114:50"/>dyuers of them are mere temporall. And neuertheles it is ferther decreed there that Archebyſſhoppes / &amp; Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes / and other prelates ſhall nat appere wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be called before the kyng or his Iuſtices for ſuch cauſes for ſo moche that ther is no power ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to the laye / to iuge the lordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted / but ought of neceſſyte to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beye them / and than for reformynge of ſuche thynges / the Conſtitucion gyueth ſtrayte proces agaynſte the kynges baylyffes and offycers / and agaynſt the clerkes that do make the writtes of attacheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or diſtreſſes with great excomunicacions and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdictions / and fynally procede ſo farre that they ſette the kynges lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in a certayne circuit therin lymy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnder interdiction / but he vpon the admonicyon of the Byſſhoppes reforme ſuche thynges / and it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter decreed / that if the Byſſhoppe or eccleſyaſtical iuge or inferiour pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late be compelled by ſuche diſtreſſes
<pb facs="tcp:19114:51"/>to appere / and the Actes of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be than requyred of him: ſo that it may appere therby / whether he hath proceded in any of the ſeyde caſes or lyke / or if othes / excuſations / or put gacyons / be required therin / that he ſhall in nowyſe exhibyt his Actes or gyue any othe / for that the partyes maye brige the Actes forth. &amp;c. And why any ſuch lawes ſhulde be made that they ſhuld nat in ſuch caſe ſhew their Actes or proces / ne make anye othe before the kyng or his iuſtyces. I can nat parceyue the verye cauſe / but that they be of lykelyhode very lothe to haue it examyned. What is their verye Iuriſdiccyon and what nat. Thus haue I recyted parte of the ſeyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion / and remytte the reſydue to theym that wyll take the payn to rede it. And ſurely they that ſo do / ſhall ſe dyuers harde and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme clauſes &amp; Actycles in it. And if they and ſuch other lyke were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed / I thike it were right good
<pb facs="tcp:19114:51"/>and expedient / as well for the clergye as for the people.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xxviii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Conſtitucyon in the .v. boke / and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tytle of paynes / whiche begineth / <hi>Euenit et infra</hi> wherby it is decreed thꝰ The laye ſhalde compelled precyſely by ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of excomunicacion to paye all maner penalyties / as well corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as pecunarye / whiche they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to by their prelaties / and they that wyl let or ſtoppe ſuch penalyties to be payde / ſhalde puniſſhed by ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of interdiction and excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation / &amp; than if the proces be made vnto the diſtraynyng of prelattes for that cauſe / let proces be made againſt the diſtreyners by the penalyties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in that behalfe / and how farre that Conſtitution is agaynſt the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges lawes and his prerogatyfe / and
<pb facs="tcp:19114:52"/>how farre it pretendeth aboue the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirituall turiſdiction / and agaynſt all lawes that haue ben made in tyme paſte / concernynge the ſpitytuall turiſdiction / it wyll appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to all that wyll take the payne to rede them / and if it ſhulde ſtande in ſtrength / it ſhulde folowe thervpon that if a man were enioyned by his prelatte to paye damages for a treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas / or a dyſſeaſon / or to paye a dette or a certayne ſome of money for a co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenaunt broke or ſuch other / he ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be compelled to paye it / and they that wolde let it ſhulde be enterdit &amp; excomunicate / as appereth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne letter of the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion / and ſo ſhulde the ſpirytuall courte haue power to holde plee and gyue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vpon mere Temporall thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / &amp; therfore the makers of the ſaid Conſtitucion by the makynge therof gaue a great occaſyon to haue all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyberties &amp; iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as they had kynges grauntes / and by the
<pb facs="tcp:19114:52"/>cuſtome of the realme taken fro them But yet if the prelates and Clergye that nowe be / wyll indeuour them to refourme ſuche thinges / than the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge therof can nat be layd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxix. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>f a man reporte vntruely / that prelates and ſpirituall Iuges / holde plee for the Tytell of Patronage / of cattell / and of other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges apparteynynge to the Kynges courte / wherby the prelates and ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall Iuges be blaſphemed &amp; hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I thynke an accyon lyeth in the kynges lawes agaynſt him that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that vntrue reporte / and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe prelates haue made a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitucyon / that ſuch reporters ſhalbe openly accurſed / as ſtriuers againſt the churches lyberties / vnto ſuche tyme that they haue recompenſed the Iuges and alſo the parties for their
<pb facs="tcp:19114:53"/>expences and damages. And ſurely if ſpirytuall Iuges execute that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitucyon / and compell a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to make reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence in that behalfe / they re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in to the premunire / for the ſhad none auctoritie to make that decre. And it is nat the very charytable waye / ne the waye to gyue good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to the people / ne to enduce them to ſufferau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and forberige of other: to ſe their prelates vpon ſo lyght offences ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke lawes / for reuengynge of their owne quarelles / and to deſyre to be their owne Iuges therin. And the ſeyd conſtitucion is in the fyfth boke and in the tytle agaynſte grefes / and begynneth: For as moche as it hath ben. et cetera.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxx. chapiter.</head>
            <p>IF a preſt craftely imagynnynge to Intrude in to the benyfyce of a nother / afferme that the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of the benefyce is deed / or hath
<pb facs="tcp:19114:53"/>reſygned / and therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he procureth him ſelfe to be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in to the ſame benifyce by the ſame patron that pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented the other / or his heires / and ſo taketh the profytes. The other wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knoweth of it / maye ſue him that ſo entreth as an Intruder in the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall court / for there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage bytwixte thoſe two encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes / that clayme by one patrone can nat come in debate / but if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder in ſuch caſe procure himſelfe to be preſented by another patrone / and therupon entreth and taketh the profytes / there lyeth no ſute againſt that Intruder in the ſpirituall court for there the tytle of the patronage maye come in debate bytwixte thoſe ſeuerall patrones. And yet Otho in his legantyne that begineth: Euery louer of iuſtyce. &amp;c. Puttyyg no dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyte bytwyxte Intruders that en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter by one patrone / and by ſeuerall patrones / decreeth that he which pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cureth him ſelfe to entrude / beſyde
<pb facs="tcp:19114:54"/>the reſtitucyon of damages / ſhall be forth with in the dede doynge ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded from offyce and benifyce / which thynge he wyll to be extended onely to hym that preſumeth of hys owne wyll / vyolently or priuely to inuade a benifyce / whyles another is in poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſyon / and after enforceth hym to defende the ſame. And bycauſe the ſeyde decre extendeth it ſelfe as well to make proceſſe / where the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by ſeuerall patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as by one ſelfe patron. It is againſt the kynges lawes / and wolde be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>¶ The table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat excluding of lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heryng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion made agaynſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cubinaries / is nat reaſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable. The firſt chapif. ¶ Of a conſtitucyon that ſayth / that Matrimony in the newe Teſtament
<pb facs="tcp:19114:54"/>accordeth to them that be imparfyte / The ſeconde chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtytucyon that a preſtes ſonne ſhall nat be preſented immedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after his father / and of an othe to be gyuen to the encombent wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is preſented / that he hathe nothynge gyuen for his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation The third chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtytucyon whan prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes enquere of defautes that the laye be compelled vpon payne of excomu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicatyon / to gyue an othe to ſaye the truth The fourth chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ That the prelate mediat or imedy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate / is the father ſpirituall / and that the ſpirytuall mother is the churche / whoſe ſonnes be all Catholyke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones. And of this terme church The fyfth chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ That it is troublous to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to haue two powers within the realme / wherby they may be ſued of one thynge in ſeuerall courtes &amp; by ſeuerall auctorities The .vi. chap.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:55"/>
               <item>¶ Of puttynge of preeſtes to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer afore laye men / and of Amerciame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of clerkes The ſeuenth chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the conſtitucyon of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte agans / and whether it be a ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute The eyght chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Whether both churches be voyde if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take two benyfyces without Pluralitie The nynth chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ There is a Conſtitucion that the Ordynarie ſhall nat delay a preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aboue two monethes. and whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he maye therby take the two mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethes The tenth chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ That poſſeſſyons of the churche ſhall nat be aliened / the fourme of the Canons nat obſerued The .xi. chap.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtitucyon that all they be accurſed / that letteth a woman co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert to make a wyll The .xii. Chap.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtitucyon wherby it is decreed / that clerkes may make their wylles The .xiii. chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Whether the tenth part for tythes be by the lawe of god / and of dyuers
<pb facs="tcp:19114:55"/>other thynges concernynge Tymes The .xiii. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ That the lawes of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icatyons be ſometyme vncertayne / and that there be to many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The .xv. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ If a recouery be in the Kynges courte agaynſte a dyſturbour / &amp; his Incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bent that is in poſſeſſyon / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ordinary wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kingꝭ writ cometh to him / be bounde to remoue that Incombent The .xvi. chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Whether ſent wary and clergy be by the ſpirituall auctoritye / or by the auctoritye of the kynge and his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes The .xvii. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtytucyon that is made concernynge Temporaltyes in tyme of Vacacyons / and of proces to be made therupon agaynſte the Kyng. The .xviii. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the writtes of Excomunicato Capiendo / et de Caucione recipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. And howe the kynges landes in a certayne cyrcute maye therupon be enterdyted The .xix. Chapiter.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:56"/>
               <item>¶ Of waſt done in houſes of ꝑſons and Vycars deceſſed. The .xx. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtitucyon / wherin it is recyted / that laye men be forboden as wel by the lawes of god as of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ordre the churche goodes. And of trees i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churchyardes. The .xxi. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ Of prohybitynge of preachynge The .xxii. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of ſpekynge agaynſte Decrees and Conſtitucyons / and of pylgry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages / and of worſhippynge of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and of othes The .xxiii. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ Of a Conſtitucyon / that if a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone ſleye the Parſone / or Vycare / or clerke in the church / that he ſhall leſe the patronage The .xxiiii. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ Of Clerkes that make their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonycall purgatyon / and that they ſhall be reſtored vnto their goodes vpon payne of cenſures of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che The .xxv. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of Clerkes hunters / &amp; that their Ordynaries ſhall make a mendes of their goodes. The .xxvi. chapiter.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19114:56"/>
               <item>¶ Of dyuers thynges that be preten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to be agaynſt the lyberties of the churche. And that in ſome caſe the kynges la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in the dioces may ther vpon be enterdyted. The .xxvii. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ That laye men be compelled by excomunicatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church / to pay almaner penalyties / as wel corporal as pecunari / which they be enioyned to by their prelates The .xxviii. cha.</item>
               <item>¶ That if any man reporte vntruly that they holde ple in ſpirituall cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Temporall thynges / that he ſhall be openly accurſed / as a ſtryuer agaynſt the churches lyberties The xxix. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of Intruſyons in to benefyces The .xxx. cha. ¶</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Ende of the table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Fautes in printyng.</head>
            <p>In the .xxi. cha. the firſt lefe / the .ii. ſide &amp; .xiii. lyne / rede deuide for deny In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame .xxi cha. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ii. lefe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ii. ſyde &amp; the .xiii. lyne / rede cauſe for caſe. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxii. cha. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ii. lefe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ii. ſyde. &amp;. the .xii. lyne / rede taught for thought</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
